# George P. Kontoudis

Brown Hall BB 280C, 1500 Illinois St, Golden, CO 80401, USA

★ www.georgekontoudis.com \( \times\) george.kontoudis@mines.edu \( \times\) Updated: January 6, 2024

#### RESEARCH INTERESTS

My primary research interests lie in the integration of **robotics**, **control theory**, and **machine learning**. What interests me most is the formulation of hybrid theoretical schemes and the development of novel robotic systems to bridge the gap between machine learning and autonomy. I am particularly interested in how learning algorithms and control theory can enable multiagent systems to efficiently collaborate with minimal information exchange for robotic navigation and exploration tasks.

# PROFESSIONAL & RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Assistant Professor, Colorado School of Mines Department of Mechanical Engineering	Jan 2024–present
Postdoctoral Research Associate, University of Maryland Motion and Teaming Lab (PI: Michael Otte)	Jan 2022–Dec 2023
Graduate Research Assistant, Virginia Tech Center for Marine Autonomy & Robotics (PI: Daniel J. Stilwell) Computational Multiphysics Systems Laboratory (PI: Tomonari Furukawa)	Aug 2016–Dec 2021
Undergraduate Research Assistant, National Technical University of Athens Control Systems Laboratory (PI: Kostas J. Kyriakopoulos)	Apr 2014–Mar 2016
Founder & Research Associate, OpenBionics	Sep 2014–present
EDUCATION	
Ph.D. in Electrical Engineering, Virginia Tech Dissertation Title: "Communication-Aware, Scalable Gaussian Processes for Decentralized Exploration"	2018–2021
M.S. in Mechanical Engineering, Virginia Tech Thesis Title: "Adaptive, Anthropomorphic Robot Hands for Grasping and In-Hand Manipulation"	2016–2018
Diploma (B.S. & M.S.) in Mechanical Engineering, National Technical University of Athens Thesis Title: "Design and Development of an Underactuated, Anthropomorphic Robot Hand"	2012–2016
B.S. in Mechanical Engineering, University of West Attica	2005–2010
TEACHING EXPERIENCE	
Instructor, MEGN315 Dynamics Department of Mechanical Engineering, Colorado School of Mines	Spring 2024
Instructor, ENAE488O/788O Introduction to Autonomous Multi-Robot Swarms Department of Aerospace Engineering, University of Maryland	Spring 2023
Graduate Teaching Assistant, ME4005 Mechancal Engineering Lab I Department of Mechanical Engineering, Virginia Tech	Spring 2017
Graduate Teaching Assistant, ME4006 Mechancal Engineering Lab II Department of Mechanical Engineering, Virginia Tech	Fall 2016
AWARDS & HONORS	
2022 Robotics: Science and Systems (RSS) Pioneer 2022 MRC Postdoctoral Fellowship (\$60K)  5 × IEEE Student Travel Support for IROS, ACC, and CDC  2 × Virginia Tech GSA Travel Fund Award for Humanoids and ICORR  NSF Student Travel Grant for WuWNet (\$1K)	2022 2022 2015, 2019–2021 2019, 2020 2019

NTUA Thomaideion Award for IROS	2016
Hackaday Prize, 2 <sup>nd</sup> place among 900 projects (\$10K)	2015
Robotdalen Innovation Award, 1 <sup>st</sup> place (SEK 100K)	2015

#### **INDUSTRY EXPERIENCE**

Mechanical Engineer, Sychem S.A.

Oct 2010–Aug 2015

Aircraft Maintenance Engineer Trainee, Olympic Aviation

May 2008–Jan 2010

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

### Journal Manuscripts Under Review (J:UR)

- [3] Josh Netter\*, **George P. Kontoudis**, Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis, "Decentralized Multi-Agent Motion Planning Using Cognitive Hierarchy and Gaussian Process Classification."
- [2] **George P. Kontoudis**, Daniel J. Stilwell, "Decentralized Federated Gaussian Process Training in Multi-Agent Systems with Big Data."
- [1] **George P. Kontoudis**, Daniel J. Stilwell, "Fully Decentralized, Scalable Gaussian Process Prediction for Multi-Agent Learning."

### Referred Journal Publications (J)

- [5] Zirui Xu\*, **George P. Kontoudis**, Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis, "Online and Robust Intermittent Motion Planning in Dynamic and Changing Environments," *IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks and Learning Systems*, 2023. (early access)
- [4] **George P. Kontoudis**, Stephen Krauss, Daniel J. Stilwell, "Model-Based Learning of Underwater Acoustic Communication Performance for Marine Robots," *Robotics and Autonomous Systems*, 2021.
- [3] Geng Gao, Mojtaba Shahmohammadi, Lucas Gerez, **George P. Kontoudis**, Minas Liarokapis, "On Differential Mechanisms for Underactuated, Lightweight, Adaptive Prosthetic Hands," *Frontiers in Neurorobotics*, 2021.
- [2] **George P. Kontoudis**, Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis, "Kinodynamic Motion Planning with Continuous-Time Q-Learning: An Online, Model-Free, and Safe Navigation Framework," *IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks and Learning Systems*, 2019.
- [1] **George P. Kontoudis**, Minas Liarokapis, Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis, Tomonari Furukawa, "An Adaptive Actuation Mechanism for Anthropomorphic Robot Hands," *Frontiers in Robotics and AI*, 2019.

### **Chapters in Edited Volumes (BC)**

[1] **George P. Kontoudis**, Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis, Zirui Xu\*, "RRT-QX: Real-Time Kinodynamic Motion Planning in Dynamic Environments with Continuous-Time Reinforcement Learning," in *Brain and Cognitive Intelligence: Control in Robotics*, B. Wei (Ed.), Taylor & Francis Group, CRC Press, 2022.

### Conference Papers Under Review (C:UR)

- [2] Alkesh K. Srivastava\*, **George P. Kontoudis**, Donald Sofge, Michael Otte, "Hazard Detection in Communication-Denied Environments using Bayesian Network Modeling of Path-Based Sensors."
- [1] Alkesh K. Srivastava\*, Samuel Migirditch, Mohamed Khalid M Jaffar, Carlos Nieto-Granda, Aamodh Suresh, **George P. Kontoudis**, Michael Otte, "Learning a Surrogate to Plan Paths for Information Gathering about Hazards in Dangerous Environments."

#### **Referred Conference Publications (C)**

- [17] **George P. Kontoudis**, Daniel J. Stilwell, "Decentralized Federated Learning using Gaussian Processes," *IEEE International Symposium on Multi-Robot and Multi-Agent Systems (MRS)*, Boston, USA, 2023.
- [16] **George P. Kontoudis**, Michael Otte, "Adaptive Exploration-Exploitation Active Learning of Gaussian Processes," *IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS)*, Detroit, USA, 2023.

<sup>\*</sup>denotes student mentee co-author

<sup>+</sup>denotes student advisee co-author

- [15] **George P. Kontoudis**, Michael Otte, "Closed-Form Active Learning of Expected Variance Reduction using Gaussian Process Surrogates for Adaptive Sampling," *American Control Conference (ACC)*, San Diego, USA, 2023.
- [14] Alkesh K. Srivastava\*, **George P. Kontoudis**, Donald Sofge, Michael Otte, "Distributed Multi-Robot Information Gathering using Path-Based Sensors in Entropy-Weighted Voronoi Regions," *International Symposium on Distributed Autonomous Robotic Systems (DARS)*, Montbéliard, France, 2022.
- [13] Christos N. Mavridis, **George P. Kontoudis**, John S. Baras, "Sparse Gaussian Process Regression using Progressively Growing Learning Representations," *IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC)*, Cancun, Mexico, 2022.
- [12] Josh Netter\*, **George P. Kontoudis**, Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis, "Bounded Rational RRT-QX: Multi-Agent Motion Planning in Dynamic Human-Like Environments Using Cognitive Hierarchy and Q-Learning," *IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC)*, Austin, USA, 2021.
- [11] **George P. Kontoudis**, Daniel J. Stilwell, "Decentralized Nested Gaussian Processes for Multi-Robot Systems," *IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)*, Xi'an, China, 2021.
- [10] Minas Liarokapis, **George P. Kontoudis**, "Teaching Robotic and Biomechatronic Concepts with a Gripper Design Project and a Grasping and Manipulation Competition," *IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)*, Xi'an, China, 2021.
- [9] **George P. Kontoudis**, Daniel J. Stilwell, "Prediction of Acoustic Communication Performance in Marine Robots Using Model-Based Kriging," *American Control Conference (ACC)*, New Orleans, USA, 2021.
- [8] Gal Gorjup, **George P. Kontoudis**, Anany Dwivedi, Geng Gao, Saori Matsunaga, Toshisada Mariyama, Bruce MacDonald, and Minas Liarokapis "Combining Programming by Demonstration with Path Optimization and Local Replanning to Facilitate the Execution of Assembly Tasks," *IEEE International Conference on Systems, Man and Cybernetics (SMC)*, Toronto, Canada, 2020.
- [7] **George P. Kontoudis**, Zirui Xu\*, Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis, "Online, Model-Free Motion Planning in Dynamic Environments: An Intermittent, Finite Horizon Approach with Continuous-Time Q-Learning," *American Control Conference (ACC)*, Denver, USA, 2020.
- [6] **George P. Kontoudis**, Daniel J. Stilwell, "A Comparison of Kriging and Cokriging for Estimation of Underwater Acoustic Communication Performance," *ACM International Conference on Underwater Networks and Systems (WuWNet)*, Atlanta, USA, 2019.
- [5] **George P. Kontoudis**, Minas Liarokapis, Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis, "An Adaptive, Humanlike Robot Hand with Selective Interdigitation: Towards Robust Grasping and Dexterous, In-Hand Manipulation," *IEEE-RAS International Conference on Humanoid Robots (Humanoids)*, Toronto, Canada, 2019.
- [4] **George P. Kontoudis**, Minas Liarokapis, Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis, "A Compliant, Underactuated Finger for Anthropomorphic Hands," *IEEE/RAS-EMBS Inter. Conference on Rehabilitation Robotics (ICORR)*, Toronto, Canada, 2019.
- [3] **George P. Kontoudis**, Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis, "Robust Kinodynamic Motion Planning using Model-Free Game-Theoretic Learning," *American Control Conference (ACC)*, Philadelphia, USA, 2019.
- [2] Kyriakos D. Tsoukalas, **George P. Kontoudis**, Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis, "Active-Bayesian Learning for Cooperation Connectivity in Dynamic Cyber-Physical-Human Systems," *IEEE Symposium on Adaptive Dynamic Programming and Reinforcement Learning (ADPRL)*, Honolulu, USA, 2017.
- [1] **George P. Kontoudis**, Minas Liarokapis, Agisilaos G. Zisimatos, Christoforos I. Mavrogiannis, Kostas J. Kyriakopoulos, "Open-Source, Anthropomorphic, Underactuated Robot Hands with a Selectively Lockable Differential Mechanism: Towards Affordable Prostheses," *IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS)*, Hamburg, Germany, 2015.

#### Preprints (P)

[1] **George P. Kontoudis**, Daniel J. Stilwell, "Fully Decentralized, Scalable Gaussian Processes for Multi-Agent Federated Learning," *arXiv preprint*, *arXiv*:2203.02865, 2022.

# Referred Workshop Publications (W)

[2] Alkesh K. Srivastava\*, **George P. Kontoudis**, Donald Sofge, Michael Otte, "Path-Based Sensors: Will the Knowledge of Correlation in Random Variables Accelerate Information Gathering?" *IEEE International Conference on Robotics and* 

- Automation (ICRA), Workshop on Communication Challenges in Multi-Robot Systems: Perception, Coordination, and Learning, London, UK, June 2023.
- [1] **George P. Kontoudis**, "Scalable Multi-Robot Active Exploration," *Robotics: Science and Systems (RSS), Pioneers Work-shop*, New York City, USA, June 2022.

#### Theses (T)

- [3] **George P. Kontoudis**, "Communication-Aware, Scalable Gaussian Processes for Decentralized Exploration," *Doctoral Dissertation, Virginia Tech*, USA, December 2021.
- [2] **George P. Kontoudis**, "Adaptive, Anthropomorphic Robot Hands for Grasping and In-Hand Manipulation," *Master Thesis, Virginia Tech*, USA, December 2018.
- [1] **George P. Kontoudis**, "Design and Development of an Underactuated, Anthropomorphic Robot Hand," *Diploma Thesis*, *National Technical University of Athens*, March 2016. (in Greek)

### **Technical Reports (TR)**

- [2] **George P. Kontoudis**, Minas Liarokapis, Agisilaos G. Zisimatos, Christoforos I. Mavrogiannis, Kostas J. Kyriakopoulos, "How to Create Affordable, Anthropomorphic, Light-Weight Prosthetic Hands," *Control Systems Lab, National Technical University of Athens*, Athens, Greece, October 2015.
- [1] Agisilaos G. Zisimatos, Minas Liarokapis, Christoforos I. Mavrogiannis, **George P. Kontoudis**, Kostas J. Kyriakopoulos, "How to Create Affordable, Modular, Light-Weight, Underactuated, Compliant Robot Hand," *Control Systems Lab*, *National Technical University of Athens*, Athens, Greece, January 2015.

#### **TALKS & PRESENTATIONS**

- · "Decentralized Federated Learning using Gaussian Processes," *IEEE International Symposium on Multi-Robot and Multi-Agent Systems (MRS)*, Boston, USA, 2023. [Oral Presentation]
- · "Adaptive Exploration-Exploitation Active Learning of Gaussian Processes," *IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS)*, Detroit, USA, 2023. [Oral & Poster Presentation]
- · "Closed-Form Active Learning Using Expected Variance Reduction of Gaussian Process Surrogates for Adaptive Sampling" American Control Conference (ACC), San Diego, USA, 2023. [Oral Presentation]
- · "Decentralized Gaussian Process Learning for Exploration with Multi-Robot Systems" *Maryland Robotics Center Research Symposium*, College Park, USA, May 2023. [Oral Presentation Invited Talk]
- · "Scalable Exploration-Exploitation Active Learning of Gaussian Process Surrogates for Adaptive Sampling" *Maryland Robotics Center Research Symposium*, College Park, USA, May 2023. [Poster Presentation]
- · "Multi-Robot Adaptive Sampling using Decentralized Gaussian Processes," *International Symposium on Distributed Autonomous Robotic Systems (DARS)*, Monbeliard, France, November 2022. [Poster Presentation]
- · "Scalable Multi-Robot Active Exploration," *Robotics: Science and Systems (RSS)*, *Pioneers Workshop*, New York City, USA, June 2022. [Spotlight Presentation]
- · "Communication-Aware, Scalable Gaussian Processes for Decentralized Exploration" *Bradley Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering, Virginia Tech*, Blacksburg, USA, December 2021. [PhD Defense]
- · "Decentralized Nested Gaussian Processes for Multi-Robot Systems," *IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)*, Xi'an, China, 2021. [Virtual Presentation]
- · "Online, Model-Free Motion Planning in Dynamic Environments: An Intermittent, Finite Horizon Approach with Continuous-Time Q-Learning," *American Control Conference (ACC)*, Denver, USA, 2020. [Rapid-Interactive Presentation]
- · "A Comparison of Kriging and Cokriging for Estimation of Underwater Acoustic Communication Performance," *ACM International Conference on Underwater Networks and Systems (WuWNet)*, Atlanta, USA, 2019. [Oral Presentation]
- · "An Adaptive, Humanlike Robot Hand with Selective Interdigitation: Towards Robust Grasping and Dexterous, In-Hand Manipulation," *IEEE-RAS Intern. Conference on Humanoid Robots (Humanoids)*, Toronto, Canada, 2019. [Poster Presentation]
- · "Robust Kinodynamic Motion Planning using Model-Free Game-Theoretic Learning," *American Control Conference (ACC)*, Philadelphia, USA, 2019. [Oral Presentation]
- · "A Compliant, Underactuated Finger for Anthropomorphic Hands," *IEEE/RAS-EMBS International Conference on Rehabilitation Robotics (ICORR)*, Toronto, Canada, 2019. [Poster Presentation]
- · "Adaptive, Anthropomorphic Robot Hands for Grasping and In-Hand Manipulation," *Department of Mechanical Engineering, Virginia Tech*, Blacksburg, USA, December 2018. [Master's Defense]

- · "Evaluation Strategies of Adaptive, Anthropomorphic Robot Hands for Dexterous In-Hand Manipulation: Early Results," National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST), USA, 2018. [Invited Talk]
- · "Open-Source, Anthropomorphic, Underactuated Robot Hands with a Selectively Lockable Differential Mechanism: Towards Affordable Prostheses," IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS), Hamburg, Germany, 2015. [Oral Presentation]

# **SERVICE ACTIVITIES**

SERVICE ACTIVITIES	
Conference Committees	
· General Chair, Robotics: Science and Systems (RSS), Pioneers Workshop	2023
· Program Committee Member, Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI), Student Abstract and Poster	2023, 2024
· Online Platform Chair, Conference on Robot Learning (CoRL)	2022
Reviewer, Journals	
· IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks and Learning Systems	2019–2022
· IEEE Transactions on Robotics	2020, 2023
· IEEE Transactions on Automatic Control	2023
· International Journal of Robotics Research	2023
· IEEE Transactions on Automation Science and Engineering	2020-2023
· IEEE Journal of Oceanic Engineering	2023
· IEEE Transactions on Cybernetics	2020
· IEEE Transactions on Systems, Man and Cybernetics: Systems	2021
· IEEE Computational Intelligence Magazine	2020
· IEEE Control Systems Letters	2019, 2020
· IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters	2019, 2022, 2023
· IEEE Robotics & Automation Magazine	2022
· Autonomous Robots	2022
· Frontiers in Artificial Intelligence	2021
· Frontiers in Robotics and AI	2022
· Journal of Optimization Theory and Applications	2021
· International Journal of Advanced Robotic Systems	2015, 2016
Reviewer, Conferences	
· IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)	2018–2024
· IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS)	2018–2023
· American Control Conference (ACC)	2018–2021
· IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC)	2019, 2020, 2023
· IEEE International Conference on Automation Science and Engineering (CASE)	2019
· IEEE-RAS International Conference on Humanoid Robots (Humanoids)	2019
· IEEE International Conference on Biomedical Robotics and Biomechatronics (BioRob)	2018, 2020, 2021
· European Control Conference (ECC)	2022
Mediterranean Conference on Control and Automation (MED)	2018
MENTORING	

# N

# **PhD Students**

· Joshua Netter, Georgia Institute of Technology Publications: C-[12], J:UR-[3]

2020-2023

# **Master's Students**

· Alkesh K. Srivastava 2022-2023

Publications: C-[14], W-[2], C:UR-[1], C:UR-[2] Currently: PhD Student, Temple University

· Zirui Xu 2018-2020

Publications: C-[7], BC-[1], J-[5] Currently: PhD Candidate, University of Michigan